The problem we're trying to solve here is to count the number of
المشكلة التي نحاول حلها هنا هي عدّ المرات
times we need to roll five dice to get a Yahtzee.
التي علينا فيها إلقاء خمسة أحجار نرد للحصول على "ياتسي".
Five dice might seem a little bit too complicated,
قد يبدو التعامل مع خمسة أحجار نرد معقداً بعض الشيء،
so a good idea is to start simple.
لذا يُفضل البدء بشيء بسيط.
Let's assume we're only rolling two dice for now.
لنفترض أننا نرمي حجريّ نرد فقط للوقت الحالي.
And the goal is to count and return the number
والهدف هو عدّ وإرجاع
of rolls we need until we get those two dice to match.
عدد الرميات اللازم للحصول على رمية يتطابق فيها النردان.
Once we figure out the code for that,
ما إن نتوصل إلى التعليمات البرمجية المناسبة لاحتساب ذلك،
we can then modify it and add more dice to it and solve the actual problem.
يمكننا تعديلها وإضافة المزيد من أحجار النرد لحل المشكلة الأصلية.
When writing code for a complicated problem,
عند كتابة تعليمات برمجية لمعالجة مشكلة معقدة،
it's always a good idea to break it down that way.
فإنه من المفيد دائماً تيسيطه بهذه الطريقة.
Think of an abstract or simple version of the problem.
فكّروا في نسخة مجرّدة أو مبسّطة من تلك المشكلة،
Write the code you need to solve that,
ثم اكتبوا الكود اللازم لحل تلك النسخة،
and then build on that code till you solve the actual problem you have.
ثم طوّروا ذلك الكود إلى أن تحلوا المشكلة الأصلية.
To count the number of rolls needed for two dice to match,
لإيجاد عدد الرميات اللازمة لتطابق حجريّ نرد،
we will be declaring this function called keepRolling.
سنقوم بتعريف دالة اسمها keepRolling.
It doesn't take any input arguments,
هذه الدالة لا تستقبل أية وسيطات إدخال،
and it returns an integer value which is the number of rolls needed.
وتُرجع عدداً صحيحاً ألا وهو عدد الرميات اللازمة.
To simulate the dice rolling,
لمحاكاة رمي أحجار النرد،
we'll be using the function rollDice that we've created in the previous lesson.
سنستخدم الدالة rollDice التي أنشأناها في الدرس السابق.
rolleDice returns a random number
تُرجع الدالة rollDice عدداً عشوائياً يتراوح ما بين 1 و6
Here we're calling it twice,
نحن هنا نستدعي الدالة مرتين،
and setting them into the variables dice1 and dice2.
ونُسند القيمة المُرجعة إلى المتغيّرين dice1 و dice2.
Then I'll declare another integer variable
ثم سأعرّف متغيراً آخر من نوع العدد الصحيح هنا
here that we'll keep track of the number of rolls.
سيتتبع عدد الرميات.
I'll initialized it to 1 because so far,
سأهيئه بإسناد الرقم 1 له لأننا رمينا هذين النردين مرة واحدة حتى الآن.
Next, we need to keep re-rolling our dice every time they don't match.
بعد ذلك، علينا متابعة رمي حجريّ النرد في كل مرة لا يتطابقان فيها.
We could use a while loop that checks if the dice don't match,
يمكننا استخدام حلقة "while" تتأكد مما إذا كان حجري النرد غير متطابقين،
and then re-roll the dice inside.
ثم إعادة رمي حجريّ النرد داخل كتلة "while".
That is while dice1 and dice2 are not equal,
أي أنه طالما أن dice1 وdice2 غير متساويين،
then we want to retry rolling our dice and hope for a match.
علينا إعادة محاولة وعقد الأمل على حصول تطابق.
So inside our while loop,
أي أنه داخل حلقة "while"،
we'll just call this rollDice function again for dice1 and dice2,
سنستدعي دالة rollDice مرة أخرى لكل من dice1 وdice2،
and add 1 to count this extra roll that we did.
ونضيف 1 إلى العدّاد لنحتسب هذه الرمية الإضافية التي قمنا بها.
Remember that we only add 1 here because
تذكروا أننا نضيف 1 فقط هنا
those two calls simulate rolling those two dice just once.
لأن هذين الاستدعاءين يحاكيان رمي حجريّ النرد مرة واحدة فقط.
Eventually at some point,
وفي مرحلة ما في نهاية المطاف،
those two rolls would return the same value,
ستُرجع هتين الرميتين القيمة ذاتها،
and dice1 would match dice2,
وسيتطابق حجر النرد الأول مع حجر النرد الثاني،
and this while loop would end.
وستنتهي حلقة "while" هذه.
At that point, we could safely return the number
في تلك المرحلة، يمكننا إرجاع قيمة العدّاد التي احتسبناها حتى الآن،
would indicate the number of rolls we needed to get that match. That looks pretty good.
والتي ستشير إلى عدد الرميات التي احتجنا إليها للحصول على ذلك التطابق.
Let's trace that code with some examples and see if it works.
دعنا نتتبع هذا الكود باستخدام بعض الأمثلة لنرى إن كان فعّالاً.
So the first thing that happens here is we call
إذن، أول ما يحدث هنا هو استدعاء دالة "rollDice"
Let's say that randomly returned the number 4.
لنفترض أنها أرجعت الرقم 4 عشوائياً.
The next line calls rollDice again for dice2.
السطر التالي يستدعي "rollDice" مرة أخرى ويخزن القيمة في "dice2".
Let's say that returned 2.
ولنفترض أن الدالة أرجعت الرقم 2.
So dice1 has 4 in it,
أي أن المتغير "dice1" يحمل الرقم 4،
and dice2 has 2 in it.
والمتغير "dice2" يحمل الرقم 2.
And then we initialize the count variable to 1,
ثم نهيّئ متغيّر العد بإسناد الرقم 1 إليه،
and then we go to our while condition.
ومن ثم ننتقل إلى شرط "while".
It's checking if dice1 and dice2 are not the same.
إنه يتحقق مما إذا كانت قيمتا المتغيران dice1 وdice2 غير متساويين.
In this case, 4 and 2 are not the same,
وفي هذه الحالة، العددان 4 و2 غير متساويين،
so our loop condition is true which means we step inside our loop,
لذا تكون نتيجة تقييم شرط الحلقة هي "true" وعليه فإننا ننتقل إلى داخل كتلة الحلقة،
and we re-roll our dice,
حيث نعيد رمي حجريّ النرد،
calling rollDice twice again,
ونستدعي الدالة "rollDice" مرتين أخريين،
and updating the dice values 1 and 2.
ونحدّث قيمتيّ المتغيّرين 1 و2.
So let's say this time dice1 became 6,
لنفترض أن قيمة dice1 أصبحت 6،
and dice2 became 5,
وقيمة dice2 أصبحت 5،
and then after that, we add 1 to our variable count,
وبعد ذلك نضيف 1 إلى متغيّر العدّاد count،
updating it to become 2 instead of 1.
بحيث تصبح قيمته 2 بدلًا من 1.
Where each the closing brackets of the while loop,
نصل إلى القوس المتعرج الذي يختتم حلقة "while"،
so we go back up and then we perform this comparison again.
لذا نعود إلى الأعلى وننفذ هذه المقارنة من جديد.
Our dice1 and dice2 not the same.
Dice1 وDice2 ليسا متساويان؟
Well, 6 and 5 are not the same, so that's true.
حسناً، 6 لا تساوي 5، إذن فهذا صحيح.
So we step inside our loop again,
وعليه ننزل إلى مستوى الحلقة مرة أخرى،
and we update dice1 and dice2 using the rollDice again.
ونقوم بتحديث dice1 و dice2 باستخدام دالة "rollDice" مجدداً.
Let's say this time, we got 2 and 3.
لنفترض أننا حصلنا هذه المرة على 2 و3.
We add 1 to the count again,
نضيف 1 لمتغيّر العداد count مرة أخرى،
updating it to 3.
فتصبح قيمته 3.
And then we go back up and perform our loop condition.
ثم نعود للأعلى وننفذ شرط الحلقة.
We check if dice1 and dice2 are not the same,
نتحقق مما إذا كانت قيمة المتغير dice1 تساوي قيمة المتغير dice2،
and 2 and 3 are not the same,
و2 لا تساوي 3،
so that's true which means we step inside our loop again.
وعليه فإن الشرط متحقق، لذا سندخل الحلقة من جديد.
And then we update dice1 and dice2 again.
ثم نحدّث dice1 و dice2 مرة أخرى.
Let's say this time we get 1 and 1,
لنفترض أننا حصلنا هذه المرة على 1 و1،
and then we add 1 to our count making it 4
ثم نضيف 1 إلى العدّاد count لتصبح قيمته 4،
which means that we've rolled our dice four times so far.
ما يعني أننا رمينا حجريّ النرد أربعة مرات حتى الآن.
And then we go back up and do our loop condition comparison.
ثم نعود إلى الأعلى لإجراء مقارنة شرط الحلقة.
This time, dice1 and dice2 are the same.
هذه المرة، dice1 وdice2 متساويان.
So this check here evaluates to false which means our while loop is no
لذا تصبح نتيجة تقييم هذه المقارنة هي "false"،
And since we only have this return count after the loop,
ولأنه لا يوجد شيء بعد الحلقة سوى عبارة "return count"،
so that means we return 4.
فهذا يعني أننا سنُرجع العدد 4.
Basically stating that we needed four rolls of those two dice until we got a match.
وهذا يعني أننا احتجنا إلى رمي حجري النرد 4 مرات لنحصل على التطابق.
Now can you think of what we need to change in this code
والآن هل يمكنك التفكير فيما علينا تغييره في هذا الكود
here to make it work for three dice instead of two?
لجعله قادر على التعامل مع ثلاثة أحجار نرد بدلًا من اثنين؟